<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-12-22T15:50:21+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Strong Towns Ottawa</title><subtitle>A website for Strong Towns Ottawa</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Is Keeping Taxes Low Affordable?</title><link href="/2025/12/09/is-keeping-taxes-low-affordable.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Keeping Taxes Low Affordable?" /><published>2025-12-09T22:41:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-09T22:41:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/12/09/is-keeping-taxes-low-affordable</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/12/09/is-keeping-taxes-low-affordable.html"><![CDATA[<p>We constantly hear about <strong>affordability</strong> these days, if you’ve been listening to the 2026 Budget talks you’ve probably heard a lot of it. Typically the only topic regarding affordability that is touched on is with regards to property taxes, but is that really the only way our 2026 Budget affects affordability in our city?</p>

<p>We have worked together with other groups as part of the Peoples Official Plan coalition to provide feedback on the upcoming City of Ottawa 2026 Budget. We think that much of the conversation is being missed when focusing so narrowly on “affordability”. From aspects such as housing, transportation, infrastructure maintenance, community services, the environment, and more, <strong>budgets like this proposed one will not make life more affordable for residents of Ottawa.</strong></p>

<p>The letter is included here, and we strongly recommend you contacting your <a href="https://ottawa.ca/en/city-hall/mayor-and-city-councillors">councillor and the mayor</a> to tell them how you feel about the proposed 2026 Budget.</p>

<p>09 December 2025</p>

<p>Ottawa City Council<br />
110 Laurier Avenue W<br />
Ottawa, ON K1P 1J1</p>

<p>RE: Feedback on 2026 Draft Budget</p>

<p>Dear Mayor Sutcliffe and Councillors,</p>

<p>We appreciate the opportunity to comment on the 2026 budget for the City of Ottawa.</p>

<p>At the Peoples Official Plan Coalition (POP) we focus on providing a livable Ottawa for current and future residents. While many factors play a role in livability, such as safety, opportunities for jobs, good transportation, housing options, etc… one of the largest factors is affordability.</p>

<p>POP stands with groups who are working with those residents most marginalized by increased unaffordability in Ottawa, including supporting the budget requests and priorities coming from the <strong>Alliance to End Homelessness</strong>, <strong>CAWI-IVTF</strong>, and the <strong>Ottawa Community
Food Partnership</strong>, all noting the need to prioritize the specific municipal responsibilities and levers to ensure affordable housing, transportation, and food.</p>

<p>POP additionally feels it is important to address middle class homeowners in Ottawa, and how the conversation on affordability in the City’s budget only looks at the immediate impact of taxes on residents. While this is obviously an important aspect, it only speaks to a small part of the bigger picture of affordability.</p>

<p>As per the City of Ottawa’s 2026 Budget Magazine, the proposed increase will result in “an average property tax bill increase of <strong>$166</strong> for urban homeowners and <strong>$108</strong> for rural homeowners.” This is certainly not a small amount by any means, but we would like to zoom out a bit and see how this compares to the costs that residents will bear due to underfunded services on which they rely. For reference, the $166 for urban homeowners would work out to approximately <strong>7$ a month</strong> per person in a household with 2 breadwinners.</p>

<p>One of the largest costs for families is <strong>transportation</strong>, car ownership is costing the average Canadian about <strong>$16,000/year per car</strong>. Many households are forced to purchase and maintain 2 or more vehicles due to their lack of alternative options. Our under-investment into alternative transportation modes such as public transit, safe cycling, and pedestrian infrastructure has forced residents to rely on the most expensive form of transportation
available. Even if they don’t own a car, unreliability in our transit system often leads to payinghigh prices for Ubers. These are costs that our residents wouldn’t have to bear if they were given safe, reliable, and effective transportation alternatives.</p>

<p>The largest expense in the lives of residents is <strong>housing</strong>. We are saddened to see that the amount the city will be contributing to building affordable housing has <strong>dropped by over $6 million dollars</strong> since 2024. We need both market and non-market solutions to help alleviate this housing crisis we face. Adding more non-market housing will help bring down prices for those who are living in market housing as well. By giving residents more options we are ensuring that they are able to continue contributing to the vibrant city that we live in.</p>

<p>A budget oriented toward affordability would invest deeply into <strong>climate resiliency</strong>. The climate resiliency strategy that Council recently passed, Climate Ready Ottawa (CRO), outlines numerous threats posed by climate change as well as their consequences. To take one example: severe Ottawa River flooding in 2017 and 2019 resulted in <strong>$2.6 million in direct costs</strong> to the City of Ottawa and <strong>$223 million in insured damages</strong> in eastern Ontario and western Quebec. This is to say nothing of uninsured damages, or unquantified effects on life and wellbeing. Similarly, the 2022 derecho incurred damages of <strong>$24.1 million to the City</strong> and <strong>$720 million in insurance claims</strong>. The draft budget doesn’t mention CRO, nor whether the City is funding the mere $5 million per year requested for its proposed actions that strengthen resiliency from <strong>other effects of climate change, whether extreme heat, drought, disease, or wildfire smoke</strong>. And investments in resiliency yield substantial returns, as prevention typically does: as CRO describes, “Environment and Climate Change Canada estimates that <strong>every dollar spent on proactive adaptation saves $13 to $15 in avoided recovery costs.</strong>”</p>

<p>Many interventions to increase <strong>environmental sustainability</strong> and reduce GHG emissions also increase affordability, among other goals in Ottawa’s Official Plan. Not only does supporting sustainable transportation modes, such as cycling or transit, reduce transportation costs, they also reduce the health effects of air pollution. Similarly, natural infrastructure—whether preserving natural features like wetlands and forest or building new features like native plantings, rain gardens, and bioswales—is often a fraction of the cost of “grey” infrastructure and also supports the local ecosystem, builds climate resiliency, and strengthens community.</p>

<p>Investing into our <strong>water, wastewater, and stormwater infrastructure</strong> will help ensure that residents do not have to be on the hook for catastrophic outcomes when, inevitably, the next flood happens. We have seen more and more water mains bursting which leads to a worrying trend. Taking care of our existing infrastructure ahead of disaster would mean that residents have peace of mind, and more money in their pocket for other needs. We also need to ensure we are not adding more infrastructure that cannot be maintained, as we are already struggling to make a dent in our long-term infrastructure repairs.</p>

<p>Investing into our city’s <strong>recreational facilities</strong> allows residents to avoid paying hundreds or potentially thousands of dollars a year on keeping themselves or their children active. Being physically active and healthy leads to not only a higher physical quality of life, it leads to improved mental health.</p>

<p>Earlier this year, City Council received a series of <strong>Asset Management Plans</strong> on the state of its infrastructure. The City faces, over the next ten years, a <strong>$10.2 Billion funding shortfall</strong> to maintain and replace its aging equipment and facilities. While the rate supported assets have updated their Long Term Financial Management plans, the <strong>tax supported assets, $6 Billion, have not been accounted for</strong>. The 2026 budget directions did not address these issues. These facilities will continue to get older, be closed for longer, and have their problems worsened. Our budget should be addressing the missing funding for these vital services and infrastructure; <strong>ignoring them will not lead to efficiencies, and kicking the issue down the road will only increase costs to taxpayers in the future.</strong></p>

<p>As you can see there are plenty of costs that residents have to bear when our City does not provide adequate funding for the services they need. Whether it is transportation options, housing options, greenspace, recreational facilities, or any other number of City services provided, all of them are going to cost residents a lot more to find adequate alternatives in the private sector, while still being on the hook for lackluster public options. This ends up giving us the worst of both worlds. If the City of Ottawa can find a budget that allows them to actually meet the needs of residents we are certain that even middle and upper class residents would find a lot of savings. This could come from downsizing to 1 car per household, reducing insurance costs, being able to get a membership at a City gym, rather than a private one, and much more.</p>

<p>Sincerely,</p>

<p>The Peoples Official Plan Coalition</p>

<iframe src="/uploads/2025%2012%2009%20POP%20Letter%20-%20Feedback%20on%202026%20Draft%20Budget.pdf" width="100%" height="600px" style="border: none;"></iframe>]]></content><author><name>Marko Miljusevic</name></author><category term="Finances" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We constantly hear about affordability these days, if you’ve been listening to the 2026 Budget talks you’ve probably heard a lot of it. Typically the only topic regarding affordability that is touched on is with regards to property taxes, but is that really the only way our 2026 Budget affects affordability in our city?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">December Newsletter</title><link href="/2025/12/02/December-Newsletter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="December Newsletter" /><published>2025-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/12/02/December-Newsletter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/12/02/December-Newsletter.html"><![CDATA[<iframe id="newsletter-iframe" src="https://eomail5.com/web-version?p=387e4044-cd7d-11f0-966b-7da0ce78ee0b&amp;pt=campaign&amp;t=1764640436&amp;s=13727c3908ae6289684d61b11b0a60ba02bfc5be7349c85a4f7374e669e92276" width="100%" frameborder="0" style="border: none; background: transparent; display: block;" scrolling="no" onload="resizeIframe(this)"></iframe>

<script>
function resizeIframe(iframe) {
  iframe.style.height = '6800px'; // Desktop-specific adjustment (Always adjust desktop first, once you find the correct height adjust for mobile below)
    setTimeout(function() {
    try {
      // Attempt to get dynamic height (may fail due to cross-origin-resource-sharing limitations)
      const height = iframe.contentWindow.document.body.scrollHeight;
      if (height > 100) { 
        iframe.style.height = height + 'px';
      }
    } catch (e) {
    
      console.log('Could not auto-detect height, using fallback');
    }
  }, 500);

  
  if (window.innerWidth <= 768) {
    iframe.style.height = '11600px'; // Mobile-specific adjustment (Usually 33% bigger than Desktop)
  }
}


function handleResize() {
  const iframe = document.getElementById('newsletter-iframe');
  if (iframe) {
    iframe.style.height = '100px';
    resizeIframe(iframe);
  }
}

window.addEventListener('resize', handleResize);
window.addEventListener('orientationchange', handleResize);
</script>]]></content><author><name>Etienne Lefebvre</name></author><category term="Newsletter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Recommendation On Minimum Lot Sizes</title><link href="/2025/11/21/minimum-lot-sizes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Recommendation On Minimum Lot Sizes" /><published>2025-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/11/21/minimum-lot-sizes</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/11/21/minimum-lot-sizes.html"><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0;">
  <img src="/assets/img/logo3.png" style="width: 200px; height: auto; object-fit: contain;" />
</div>

<p><strong>Below is the official feedback</strong> we submitted to the Ontario Ministry of Municipal Affairs and Housing as part of their <a href="https://ero.ontario.ca/notice/025-1100">public consultation</a> on minimum lot sizes and its impact on the housing crisis.</p>

<hr />
<p>To whom it may concern,</p>

<p>We appreciate the opportunity to comment on the proposed Provincial Planning Statement. We write from the perspective of a group committed to building a resilient, people-focused Ottawa. The PPS is an important opportunity to shift provincial planning away from financially complex, speculative growth patterns that result in a burden to municipalities, and toward a more incremental, fiscally responsible approach that strengthens existing places.</p>

<p><strong>1. Benefits and risks of reducing/removing minimum lot sizes</strong><br />
Reducing or removing minimum lot sizes in serviced urban areas enables much desired gentle density, increases housing supply, and broadens ownership options by lowering the land cost per home. It also strengthens municipal finances by allowing more households to share existing infrastructure instead of pushing growth to expensive new subdivisions. The main risks – pressures on aging infrastructure, neighbourhood resistance, and poorly designed small-lot development – can be reasonably managed through predictable form-based rules and updated servicing plans. These concerns are reasons to regulate form and servicing and not to retain large, exclusionary lot-size minimums.</p>

<p><strong>2. Best practices from other jurisdictions</strong><br />
Places that have successfully reformed lot-size rules (New Zealand 2020, Oregon 2022, Texas 2023) pair relaxed minimums with simple, predictable standards for building form, scale, and servicing. They focus on how buildings meet the street, instead of arbitrary lot dimensions. They also allow small-scale builders to participate by making approvals straightforward and by making sure different housing types do not get outlawed by regulations. The recipe seems to be consistent: remove lot-size barriers, but replace them with clear rules for height, setbacks, massing, and basic environmental performance so infill is both incremental and compatible.</p>

<p><strong>3. Situations where minimum lot sizes remain necessary</strong><br />
Minimum lot sizes are absolutely defensible where they directly protect public health and safety – such as areas dependent on wells and septic systems, floodplains, mapped unstable soils, or parcels that cannot meet emergency access or stormwater requirements without a certain minimum area. On most serviced urban lands, however, lot-size minimums function as de facto barriers to different housing solutions.</p>

<p><strong>4. Suggested smallest urban lot size and its implications</strong><br />
A reasonable provincial guideline for fully serviced urban parcels should permit lots as small as 6 m frontage with no restriction for area. This supports a wide range of missing-middle forms while preserving room for basic servicing. The opportunities include more attainable starter homes, more housing diversity, and more efficient use of existing infrastructure. Limitations would be a reduced private yard space, tighter tree-planting conditions, and potential parking pressures. All those can be addressed through complementary performance standards. Frontage and how the building meets the street should be treated as an integrated package, ensuring that parcels remain buildable, functional, and compatible with their context.</p>

<p><strong>5. Supporting zoning and performance standards</strong><br />
To make reduced lot-size rules successful, municipalities should permit additional residential units and small multiplexes as-of-right, remove parking minimums in their urban perimeters, and apply simple form-based standards for height, setbacks, lot coverage, and massing. Environmental performance should include a mix of minimum permeable surface with low-impact stormwater requirements and basic tree-planting standards.Municipalities should also plan to streamline approvals in order to enable many small, incremental projects rather than relying solely on large developments to meet their housing goals. These measures ensure that smaller lots remain developable, and contribute to a fiscally productive area.</p>

<p>In conclusion, Ontario has in its hands an opportunity to re-orient its planning framework toward financially productive, people-centered, future-proof communities. A PPS grounded in infill-first growth, gentle density,transit alignment, and incremental development will create places that are prosperous, affordable, resilient, and able to weather economic uncertainty.</p>

<p>Thank you for considering this submission.</p>

<p>Sincerely,<br />
<strong>Strong Towns Ottawa</strong><br />
<em>November 21st, 2025</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Letters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are Buses Only Delayed at Peak Hours?</title><link href="/2025/11/08/are-buses-only-delayed-at-peak-hours.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are Buses Only Delayed at Peak Hours?" /><published>2025-11-08T05:53:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-08T05:53:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/11/08/are-buses-only-delayed-at-peak-hours</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/11/08/are-buses-only-delayed-at-peak-hours.html"><![CDATA[<p>Since the recent open house for the Bank Street Active Transportation Study, which you can read my summary of <a href="https://strongtownsottawa.ca/2025/09/25/the-city-needs-to-be-bold-with-bank.html">here</a>, I have heard the idea that the peak hour bus lanes are all that’s needed.</p>

<p>Typically the opinion is that surely the delays for the buses must be at the same time as when cars are the most delayed. The reasoning for this is most likely that many of these people don’t actually ride the bus outside of those hours, or they don’t ride the bus at all, and assume that the delays for cars and buses must be occurring at the same times.</p>

<p>While I can understand where the thought might be coming from, it’s important to refer to the data on this so we can make sure we’re correctly deciding on how to use such an important bit of space.</p>

<p>Thankfully we have data from OC Transpo, so we don’t have to guess as to when delays are the worst for 2 of our 3 busiest bus routes in the city.</p>

<h3 id="what-does-the-data-say">What does the data say?</h3>

<p>A member of ours (<a href="https://bsky.app/profile/alex-is.online">Alex</a>) put together a table that very clearly shows major delays for routes 6 and 7 outside of when the city considers “peak hours” for their current proposal.</p>

<p>The table indicates the times it takes for the buses to get through the section of Bank where the study is located (from Aylmer to Catherine street).</p>

<p>You can see in the following image, we have the “peak hours” that the city proposes for bus lanes North-bound and South-bound surrounded by the double black lines.</p>

<p>It is clear that while the buses definitely start getting delayed North-bound from 7-9am, and South-bound from 2:30-4:30pm, the worst delays going North are actually outside of when the city is proposing bus lanes at all. Likewise going South, significant delays persist all throughout the day.</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/busesOnBankDelaysDuringTheDayOutlinedTravelLaneHoursPeakHours.png" alt="busesOnBankDelaysDuringTheDayOutlinedTravelLaneHoursPeakHours.png" /></p>

<p>I had spoken to Noah Vineberg from ATU279 and anecdotally they had already told me that the worst experiences for drivers on these routes are when parking is in effect, so it’s nice to have data to back that up!</p>

<h3 id="how-about-weekends">How about weekends?</h3>

<p>I also wanted to touch on weekend delays, as it had been brought up recently with the Lansdowne 2.0 discussions, that 9-5 delays during the week weren’t too bad, and that weekends were the real issue. You will not hear me push back against bus lanes on weekends at all, but the delays on the weekend really aren’t that different from during the week.</p>

<p>As you can see below, North-bound actually looks almost exactly the same as during the week, and the only big difference is going South-bound, which adds about a minute of extra delays compared to during the week.</p>

<p>Just to be clear, this is still terrible and absolutely needs to be addressed, which is why we’re pushing for 24/7 bus lanes, which would solve both the extreme weekday AND weekend delays all at once! But we should be clear, the delay aren’t just bad “only during peak hours” or “only on weekends”, the delays are awful almost all of the time!</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/busesOnBankDelaysDuringTheWeekend.png" alt="busesOnBankDelaysDuringTheWeekend.png" /></p>

<h3 id="why-are-the-delays-so-much-worse-in-the-middle-of-the-day">Why are the delays so much worse in the middle of the day?</h3>

<p>One might think that the delay shouldn’t be too bad during weekdays outside of working hours, right? Everyone is already at work, so why are the buses being delayed? There are fewer cars on the street, shouldn’t that be great for buses?</p>

<p>The very simple answer is that during the weekdays, those “peak-hours” are actually already turned from parking lanes into travel lanes, which is why we wouldn’t actually see a large improvement from making them into bus lanes.</p>

<p>The thing that really delays our extremely important buses, and the <strong>thousands of people they move every day</strong>, are the couple of parked cars in the outer lanes. As soon as just a single car is occupying that outer lane, the bus now has to pull in, and out, of that lane every single time it has to drop-off and pick up passengers. Add up the multiple stops in just this section of Bank alone, and that leads to a LOT of delays.</p>

<h3 id="what-does-lansdowne-20-mean-for-bank">What does Lansdowne 2.0 mean for Bank?</h3>

<p>Over and over during the discussions about Lansdowne 2.0, there was a very clear issue that kept getting raised. Access to Lansdowne is extremely lackluster and needs to be improved for any chance of success for the project. Polling was done around the project, and responders identified improving transportation to and from Lansdowne as you can see below. 24/7 bus lanes are one of the only ways we could improve transportation access to Lansdowne.</p>

<p><img src="/uploads/nanosPollPrioritiesForLansdowne2RedCircle.png" alt="nanosPollPrioritiesForLansdowne2RedCircle.png" /></p>

<p>If we’re going to be investing close to half a billion dollars in this area, the very least we can do is make it easier for people from across the city to actually access. Otherwise why are we putting all of this money here?</p>

<h3 id="so-whats-the-solution">So what’s the solution?</h3>

<p>This is the beauty behind the 24/7 bus lanes, and why trying to find some “balance” between parking, of often single-occupancy, vehicles and <strong>2 of the 3 busiest buses in our city</strong>, buses which move thousands of people every single day, is going to lead to an extremely underwhelming change based on current proposals. It’s often best to just keep it as simple as possible, paint the lanes red, and let those beautiful buses ride!</p>

<h3 id="how-do-we-get-247-bus-lanes-done">How do we get 24/7 bus lanes done?</h3>

<p>Please help us by doing any or all of the following :</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Contact your <a href="https://ottawa.ca/en/city-hall/mayor-and-city-councillors">local Councillor</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Contact the <a href="https://engage.ottawa.ca/bank-street-active-transportation-and-transit-priority-feasibility-study">project team</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Share this with your friends or family</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Sign up to our <a href="https://forms.gle/EmJZcVynJ5sn1jmLA">petition</a></p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Let the project team and your Councillor know that you want more from the city. Feel free to link them this, or any of the other resources we have on this topic such as our <a href="https://strongtownsottawa.ca/bank/">Bank page</a> or the <a href="https://strongtownsottawa.ca/2025/09/25/the-city-needs-to-be-bold-with-bank.html">summary I wrote of the open house</a>, or just use any of the data/or graphs from here!</p>

<p>We strongly urge all Councillors and the city to push for fully dedicated bus lanes instead of parking lanes.</p>

<p>The proposal will most likely be going to committee sometime in the near future, so please keep an eye on that, and sign up to our petition <a href="https://forms.gle/EmJZcVynJ5sn1jmLA">here</a>. I’ll shoot you an e-mail as soon as we hear about it going to committee!</p>

<p>If you’re interested in signing up to delegate, I strongly encourage you to do so. It’s really not that scary, and you can do it online! If you have any questions about that, please do not hesitate to reach out to me about it, I’m more than happy to walk you through the process and even take a look at what you’d like to say! You can reach me at marko@strongtownsottawa.ca.</p>]]></content><author><name>Marko Miljusevic</name></author><category term="Transit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Since the recent open house for the Bank Street Active Transportation Study, which you can read my summary of here, I have heard the idea that the peak hour bus lanes are all that’s needed.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">November Newsletter</title><link href="/2025/11/03/November-Newsletter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="November Newsletter" /><published>2025-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/11/03/November-Newsletter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/11/03/November-Newsletter.html"><![CDATA[<iframe id="newsletter-iframe" src="https://eomail5.com/web-version?p=77579b5a-b6ba-11f0-8f0e-1bf7c7ba3c2b&amp;pt=campaign&amp;t=1762180907&amp;s=37f468acc535d5fb1901325661949e5d7865dfe40b334074200ceabeafcf1106" width="100%" frameborder="0" style="border: none; background: transparent; display: block;" scrolling="no" onload="resizeIframe(this)"></iframe>

<script>
function resizeIframe(iframe) {
  iframe.style.height = '8175px'; // Desktop-specific adjustment (Always adjust desktop first, once you find the correct height adjust for mobile below)
    setTimeout(function() {
    try {
      // Attempt to get dynamic height (may fail due to cross-origin-resource-sharing limitations)
      const height = iframe.contentWindow.document.body.scrollHeight;
      if (height > 100) { 
        iframe.style.height = height + 'px';
      }
    } catch (e) {
    
      console.log('Could not auto-detect height, using fallback');
    }
  }, 500);

  
  if (window.innerWidth <= 768) {
    iframe.style.height = '12000px'; // Mobile-specific adjustment (Usually 33% bigger than Desktop)
  }
}


function handleResize() {
  const iframe = document.getElementById('newsletter-iframe');
  if (iframe) {
    iframe.style.height = '100px';
    resizeIframe(iframe);
  }
}

window.addEventListener('resize', handleResize);
window.addEventListener('orientationchange', handleResize);
</script>]]></content><author><name>Etienne Lefebvre</name></author><category term="Newsletter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Open Letter on Lansdowne 2.0</title><link href="/2025/10/28/open-letter-lansdowne-2-0.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Open Letter on Lansdowne 2.0" /><published>2025-10-28T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-28T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/10/28/open-letter-lansdowne-2-0</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/10/28/open-letter-lansdowne-2-0.html"><![CDATA[<p>Strong Towns Ottawa has sent an open letter to all Councillors with our concerns regarding Lansdowne.</p>

<p>Read our letter below.</p>

<hr />

<p>Dear councillor,</p>

<p>Strong Towns Ottawa would like to express concern about the current Lansdowne 2.0 plans. While we
recognise the need for improvements, replacements, densification and proper sports and event facilities,
we are not comfortable with a number of issues.</p>

<p>Strong Towns Ottawa has argued for over a year now that <a href="https://strongtownsottawa.ca/2025/09/25/the-city-needs-to-be-bold-with-bank.html">transit access to Lansdowne has to be
improved</a>, even without the new plans. During event days, Bank Street and the surrounding area are a
nightmare for both visitors and residents. Bus schedules are becoming completely unreliable, with routes 6
and 7 having the most cancelled trips. Lansdowne 2.0 will be even worse for traffic. Visitors are stuck in
traffic with engines running. The City has committed to promoting alternative forms of transportation. The
current situation at Lansdowne does not allow for other modes to thrive. For Lansdowne 2.0 to have any
chance of success, proper public transit in the form of fully dedicated bus lanes is required.</p>

<p>We believe nudging people into transit and experiencing a fast and smooth ride is important for traffic flow
and the environment. Therefore, we strongly recommend adding permanent bus lanes on Bank Street. We
believe that current discussions about bus lanes on Bank Street in the Glebe are based on fear of the
unknown while ignoring both existing travel and parking data and the bigger picture of traffic flow and air
quality.</p>

<p>While other city infrastructure is neglected or its maintenance postponed, the city takes on debt to help
make Lansdowne a success, even after the Lansdowne partnership <a href="https://ottawacitizen.com/news/lansdowne-partnership-lost-11-1-million">posted yet another loss</a>. We are
concerned about the lower number of stadium seats, which may, and likely will, increase event ticket
prices. We believe higher ticket prices will undermine equality in our city. As consumers only have so much
to spend, higher ticket prices also means that that money can not be spent somewhere else in the city.</p>

<p>Many residents have expressed frustration about the transparency of the project. If councillors and the
media already express worries about understanding the financial consequences, how are citizens expected
to understand what happens with their tax dollars? We don’t think the City has communicated properly what
happens if the plans don’t pan out. The timelines are extraordinary and cost is always increasing.</p>

<p>What are the worst case scenarios? What if the cost is going up faster than foreseen? What if a sports
team moves on? What if bands decide on smaller venues? Given the situation south of the border, today’s
models can be worthless tomorrow. Many of us feel the plans are being ushered through Council to limit
the sound of critical voices.</p>

<p>Large city projects mean that many people and lots of public money is involved. At the tail end of LRT
phase 1, we have seen several people quietly leaving their positions after a damning report on how phase
1 was handled. A project like this should have enthusiastic support from everyone at Council. It doesn’t.
That possibly only around half of City council feels comfortable attaching their name to it, is very
concerning to us.
In short, we want to stress once again that we are not against further developing Lansdowne, in fact we
encourage it, but we are nervous about accessibility, the many assumptions that are made to justify the
cost, the way the plan is being ushered through Council, and the accountability of tax dollars being spent.</p>

<p>May we ask one question? If you are planning to vote in favour, and you were asked to invest in it with your
own money, would you remortgage your house to become a partner in Lansdowne 2.0?
Respectfully,</p>

<p>Strong Towns Ottawa</p>]]></content><author><name>Strong Towns Ottawa</name></author><category term="Letters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Strong Towns Ottawa has sent an open letter to all Councillors with our concerns regarding Lansdowne.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Automatic Speed Enforcement Cameras</title><link href="/2025/10/22/Speed-Camera-Ford.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Automatic Speed Enforcement Cameras" /><published>2025-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/10/22/Speed-Camera-Ford</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/10/22/Speed-Camera-Ford.html"><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0;">
  <img src="/assets/img/logo3.png" style="width: 200px; height: auto; object-fit: contain;" />
</div>

<p>Premier Ford,</p>

<p>We are extremely concerned about your directive to remove speed safety cameras in Ontario. Along with the Association of Municipalities, the CAA, Ontario police forces and the Ontario Traffic Safety Council, we believe in the evidence that previously collected data show: fining people who don’t comply with speed limits helps: it leads to drastic safety improvements.</p>

<p>This makes a good case for continuing the use of cameras to maintain speed compliance. The ultimate goal of speed enforcement is obviously that people adhere to speed limits. Existing data shows that speed compliance quickly improves and is maintained after cameras are installed. Fewer and fewer tickets are being issued by each camera every year.</p>

<p>This trend is already happening: in Ottawa, as the enclosed graph shows, speeds have considerably dropped at road segments where cameras have been placed. Speed cameras work! Cameras in Ottawa are overwhelmingly placed in areas near schools. Removing cameras would recreate dangerous situations in those school zones. And let’s not forget people with disabilities and our aging population, who may take longer to cross roads.</p>

<p>Many safety experts strongly support the use of automatic speed cameras as does the majority of Ontario drivers (73%). In Ottawa, speed compliance went up from 16% to 81% in speed camera zones; the instances of high end speeding in those zones went down from 14% to less than 1%. Those are amazing results.</p>

<p>Therefore we ask you to reconsider an end to speed enforcement with cameras and allow technology to do its work to protect the lives of Ontarians. Using cameras allows police officers to do other important work. This is about safety for every Ontario resident, not a cash grab.</p>

<p>Respectfully,</p>

<p>Strong Towns Ottawa</p>

<figure class="text-center">
<img src="/assets/img/speed_camera.png" />
</figure>

<figure class="text-center">
<img src="/assets/img/speed_camera_2.png" />
</figure>

<figure class="text-center">
<img src="/assets/img/speed_camera_3.png" />
</figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Letters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">October Newsletter</title><link href="/2025/10/01/October-Newsletter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="October Newsletter" /><published>2025-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/10/01/October-Newsletter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/10/01/October-Newsletter.html"><![CDATA[<iframe id="newsletter-iframe" src="https://eomail5.com/web-version?p=502d2d26-88e1-11f0-a78e-a540687d4a7d&amp;pt=campaign&amp;t=1759320096&amp;s=0e5c09e31d882985ea3d9ce7a9f027404b70c15d99d9bc69a7345e3259c69fd5" width="100%" frameborder="0" style="border: none; background: transparent; display: block;" scrolling="no" onload="resizeIframe(this)"></iframe>

<script>
function resizeIframe(iframe) {
  iframe.style.height = '7300px'; // Desktop-specific adjustment (Always adjust desktop first, once you find the correct height adjust for mobile below)
    setTimeout(function() {
    try {
      // Attempt to get dynamic height (may fail due to cross-origin-resource-sharing limitations)
      const height = iframe.contentWindow.document.body.scrollHeight;
      if (height > 100) { 
        iframe.style.height = height + 'px';
      }
    } catch (e) {
    
      console.log('Could not auto-detect height, using fallback');
    }
  }, 500);

  
  if (window.innerWidth <= 768) {
    iframe.style.height = '10300px'; // Mobile-specific adjustment (Usually 33% bigger than Desktop)
  }
}


function handleResize() {
  const iframe = document.getElementById('newsletter-iframe');
  if (iframe) {
    iframe.style.height = '100px';
    resizeIframe(iframe);
  }
}

window.addEventListener('resize', handleResize);
window.addEventListener('orientationchange', handleResize);
</script>]]></content><author><name>Etienne Lefebvre</name></author><category term="Newsletter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">November Monthly Meeting</title><link href="/2025/09/29/November-Meeting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="November Monthly Meeting" /><published>2025-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/09/29/November-Meeting</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/09/29/November-Meeting.html"><![CDATA[<figure class="text-center">
  <img src="/assets/img/november_meeting.png" width="80%" />
</figure>

<p>Our November Monthly Meeting will feature a crash course on the <strong>2026 city of Ottawa draft budget</strong>, what it means for the financial solvency of our city, and how to best get involved with the budget process, with a special highlight on <strong>delegation opportunities</strong> at upcoming city council and standing committee meetings.</p>

<p><strong>Join us for our first monthly meeting, meet new people, learn about our priorities, and consider taking that first small step to get involved. All experience levels are welcome!</strong></p>

<p>🗓️ <strong>Date:</strong> November 6, 2025<br />
🕕 <strong>Time:</strong> 6:15 PM – 7:15 PM<br />
📍 <strong>Location:</strong> St. Peter’s Lutheran Church, 400 Sparks Street</p>

<p>Strong Towns Ottawa Monthly Meetings are open to the public. Anyone can join!</p>

<p>And don’t forget to join our <strong>post-meeting hangout starting at 7:30 PM</strong> at the <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/ffa9aQZ9JHpJUiA28">3 Brasseurs pub</a> on 240 Sparks Street</p>]]></content><author><name>Etienne Lefebvre</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The City Needs to be Bold with Bank</title><link href="/2025/09/25/the-city-needs-to-be-bold-with-bank.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The City Needs to be Bold with Bank" /><published>2025-09-25T21:51:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-25T21:51:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/09/25/the-city-needs-to-be-bold-with-bank</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/09/25/the-city-needs-to-be-bold-with-bank.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/uploads/250528%20Mayfair%20Bus%20Photo%20Smaller.jpg" alt="250528 Mayfair Bus Photo Smaller.jpg" /></p>

<h2 id="last-nights-open-house">Last Night’s Open House</h2>

<p>Last night the City of Ottawa held an open house for the <a href="https://engage.ottawa.ca/bank-street-active-transportation-and-transit-priority-feasibility-study">Bank Street Study</a> that looked at improving transit, active transportation, and accessibility to Bank Street, in the section between Lansdowne and the 417. To anyone who’s familiar with <a href="https://strongtownsottawa.ca/bank/">our work</a> on this, you’ll know we want this area to be made into a wonderful area for shoppers, residents, commuters, and businesses.</p>

<p>The city presented their proposal, which seeks to turn the Northbound peak morning travel lane into a bus only lane, and likewise for the Southbound. It would also turn both outer lanes into bus-only lanes during large events (things like Redblacks games that see ~20,000+ people come to Lansdowne) on weekends, which only occur ~15 times a year according to the city. There were two very tiny sections near Fifth avenue and the bridge to Old Ottawa South that will see full 24/7 bus lanes.</p>

<h3 id="the-citys-current-proposal">The city’s current proposal</h3>

<p><img src="/uploads/OpenHouseBankStreetRedesignVisual.avif" alt="OpenHouseBankStreetRedesignVisual.avif" /></p>

<p>After the city’s presentation, where they discussed the benefits of improving transit in the corridor, about how small of a percentage (7%) of the local parking is on-street along Bank, about how under-utilized that parking is (sits less than 50% used for the majority of the day), and so many more points that would lead you to the conclusion that full dedicated bus lanes were the obvious choice, we were then presented with a watered down version that tried to “compromise”, but instead gave us a half-baked result that seeks to please “everyone” and instead pleases no one.</p>

<h2 id="how-did-people-respond">How did people respond?</h2>

<p>The city opened the floor to allow for questions and comments, and for the next hour we heard from all sorts of citizens. We heard from young students, we heard from retired citizens, we heard from Glebe residents, we heard from parents of children who want safer cycling, we heard from citizens who cycled in, pedestrians, shoppers, workers, transit riders, and more. <strong>Every single person without question (besides the BIA representative) said this project does not go far enough.</strong> Person after person got up and said we need to be bolder. They said we need to have a solution that works for everyone, and this half-measure works for nobody.</p>

<p>They pointed out that this does absolutely nothing for small and medium events like 613Flea, the farmer’s market, the winter market, concerts, smaller sporting events, etc… They pointed out that this does nothing for the students who rely on the 6 and 7 and often bus outside of “peak hours”. They pointed out that this does nothing for weekends where Bank turns into a parking lot as cars try to parallel park and slow down everyone else behind them. They pointed out that this does nothing for the other 16 hours of the day where buses are forced to pull in and out between parked cars, getting bogged down, leading to less reliable service and higher costs to run our transit system. They pointed out that cyclists will still be at risk of getting doored when trying to cycle safely along this vital corridor to visit local shops.</p>

<p>Every single group said unquestionably that they wanted more from the city, and not more parking, but more bus lanes! As someone who attends a LOT of public engagements and open houses (yes — I’m a loser) I have truly and honestly never in my life seen something this overwhelming. In a room full of close to 150 people, all we heard was rounds of applause at every single comment of the over 20+ speakers that said they wanted better bus lanes, that this vision did not represent them, and that it didn’t go far enough.</p>

<p>All that we unfortunately heard back was about finding a “balance”. But who are we balancing with? The fewer than ~140 parking spots along Bank that mostly sit un-used? The misguided opinion that those spots, and not the local residents that visit shops on a regular basis, the cyclists who come multiple times a month, the workers at the stores who rely on our deteriorating transit system, are the ones that actually make those businesses thrive? We certainly didn’t hear from anyone, besides the representative for the local BIA, that the few parking spots on Bank Street were so vital that we should under no circumstances remove any of them to make the rest of the street better and more accessible to people.</p>

<h2 id="how-vital-is-this-on-street-parking">How “vital” is this on-street parking?</h2>

<p>As we can see from the city’s data below, the on-street parking is extremely under-utilized on Bank. Generally best practices for parking usage is that you want it to not be sitting mostly empty, otherwise that space could be much better used for other needs (such as improving transit). Ideally you want your parking to be used with ~70-85% so that on each block you’ll typically have 1 or 2 spaces available for anyone to use that needs it. You also don’t want to have your parking used so much that it is impossible to find a spot, as that incentivizes people to  circle the block over and over to find parking. As you can see, the on-street parking on Bank rarely if ever gets close to that sweet spot, and is very often sitting closer to below 50%, or above 90%, a.k.a. being severely misused.</p>

<h3 id="bank-on-street-parking-north">Bank On-Street Parking North</h3>

<p><img src="/uploads/bankStreetParkingUsageGlebeNorthWithPurple.png" alt="bankStreetParkingUsageGlebeNorthWithPurple.png" /></p>

<h3 id="bank-on-street-parking-south">Bank On-Street Parking South</h3>

<p><img src="/uploads/bankStreetParkingUsageGlebeSouthWithPurple.png" alt="bankStreetParkingUsageGlebeSouthWithPurple.png" /></p>

<p><strong>Legend :</strong></p>

<p>Red : Parking under 50% utilization</p>

<p>Orange : Parking utilization between 50-60%</p>

<p>Yellow : Parking utilization between 60-75%</p>

<p>Green : Parking utilization between 75-85%</p>

<p>Purple : Parking utilization over 85%</p>

<p>A quick note about the above 90%, you’ll find that this almost only ever occurs at times when the parking is free (Sundays, and in the evenings). What this means is that we’re not actually charging appropriately for the parking at those hours, because it is being over-utilized, and someone who might really want that parking cannot get it, because people are leaving their cars in a location where they might not actually need to.</p>

<h2 id="other-parking-options">Other parking options</h2>

<p>One thing to keep in mind is the 2nd Avenue garage. It is a garage that fits as many parking spots as the the whole section of Bank Street from Lansdowne to the 417. Yet according to city data, and our own experience every time we are out there at some of the busiest times, it sits almost completely un-used. If parking was so in demand, surely this parking garage would be much more full than the data tells us it is, right?</p>

<p>Well… the data seems to tell us a different story. As you can see below, using the same colouring scheme as the on-street parking, we can quite shockingly see that there’s a LOT of red here. There is almost literally never a time where the parking is being used over 50% in the 2nd avenue garage, yet it’s less than a 10 minute walk to almost the whole section of Bank Street, almost perfectly situated right in the middle.</p>

<p>Also important to keep in mind is the below is only publicly available parking, but there are also plenty of businesses that have parking of their own. Kettleman’s, Popeye’s, McDonald’s, etc… all have their own parking lots, which means there’s even more available parking on the street that gets missed here.</p>

<p>According to city data of close to 3000 responses the vast majority of people coming to Bank are happy to walk 5-10 minutes to get to the shop they want to go, and the beautiful thing about a bit of walking is they might encounter a new shop along the way that they didn’t know about! This is wonderful for businesses, we know from plenty of data that the more people you have walking near your store the better your business does.</p>

<h3 id="second-avenue-garage-parking-floors-1-and-2-short-term">Second Avenue Garage Parking Floors 1 and 2 (Short term)</h3>

<p><img src="/uploads/bankStreetOffStreetParkingLevels1And2WithPurple.png" alt="bankStreetOffStreetParkingLevels1And2WithPurple.png" /></p>

<h3 id="second-avenue-garage-parking-floors-3-and-4-long-term">Second Avenue Garage Parking Floors 3 and 4 (Long term)</h3>

<p><img src="/uploads/bankStreetOffStreetParkingLevels3and4WithPurple.png" alt="bankStreetOffStreetParkingLevels3and4WithPurple.png" /></p>

<h3 id="574-bank-street-parking-lot-near-highway">574 Bank Street Parking Lot (Near Highway)</h3>

<p><img src="/uploads/bankStreetOffStreetParking574BankWithPurple.png" alt="bankStreetOffStreetParking574BankWithPurple.png" /></p>

<h2 id="so-where-does-this-leave-us">So where does this leave us?</h2>

<p>Currently the project is clearly not ambitious enough. It seeks to find “balance”, but the “balance” is mostly just keeping the status quo. The bus lanes will only be swapping out what were previously regular travel lanes in each direction during peak hours.</p>

<p>The numbers that the city quotes as “improvements” to transit might not jump out at you initially (they quote about 1 minute improvements), but the reason for this is because they only compare the improvements to how the transit currently runs when there are 2 travel lanes in the peak direction. What this completely misses is that much of the delays that the buses see in these areas is not during the times when the lane they are loading and unloading passengers on is a travel lane, but instead during the rest of the time when the outer lanes are parking.</p>

<p>Each time a bus has to pull in and out of a stop is adding significant delays as it tries to merge back into heavy traffic. With a corridor as busy as this, with so many cars, pedestrians, cyclists, etc… that leads to much more stress and confusion for bus operators, who already have a stressful enough job. This also leads to an extremely complicated, delayed, and potentially dangerous, experience for everyone else on the road, including drivers.</p>

<p>What this means is that during the times when we would hope to see the most significant benefit, which is during hours where parking is allowed on the outer lanes, we have done absolutely nothing to improve the situation. Yet these are the times when our transit needs the most help.</p>

<p>Our city should have done studies to see how much transit would have been improved in cases where parking was removed. The answer would have almost surely been substantially. We need to be bolder than this, the busiest bus corridor in our city, with 2 of the busiest buses in our whole network, deserve better than this. If we cannot take even the busiest bus corridor in the city and make improvements to it, what hope does our broader transit network have? Bus lanes are a quick, easy, and proven solution to making transit better.</p>

<p>24/7 bus lanes would make this street more straightforward by reducing signage, it would make it more efficient for drivers and transit users, it would help cyclists have a lane where they don’t have to worry about dooring, it would help transit users get to where they need to go quickly and efficiently, businesses would benefit by being more accessible to people, pedestrians would have better visibility on the street with no parked cars blocking their sight lines, it would cut down on parallel parking causing congestion, and SO MUCH MORE.</p>

<p>The best part of all of this, is it would only require us to move a tiny amount of the overall parking in the area off of the street, and as we’ve already seen, the rest of the parking capacity is easily able to soak all of that up, and more.</p>

<p>We strongly urge the City of Ottawa to take advantage of this opportunity to be <strong>BOLD</strong>. The current proposal is timid and too small to make a meaningful change considering how long it took to get here (the first open house was in June of last year). If we somehow end up being incorrect in our bet, then we fully support the city revisiting the project to make the necessary adjustments. This is the Strong Towns way: taking bets that are easy to implement, provide meaningful incremental change, and build up over time to further improve our beautiful city for everyone; be they a shop owner on Bank Street, a Student heading to class, a distant shopper, or a local resident.</p>]]></content><author><name>Marko Miljusevic</name></author><category term="Transit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>