<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-10-29T00:16:45+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Strong Towns Ottawa</title><subtitle>A website for Strong Towns Ottawa</subtitle><entry><title type="html">October Newsletter</title><link href="/2025/10/01/October-Newsletter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="October Newsletter" /><published>2025-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/10/01/October-Newsletter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/10/01/October-Newsletter.html"><![CDATA[<iframe id="newsletter-iframe" src="https://eomail5.com/web-version?p=502d2d26-88e1-11f0-a78e-a540687d4a7d&amp;pt=campaign&amp;t=1759320096&amp;s=0e5c09e31d882985ea3d9ce7a9f027404b70c15d99d9bc69a7345e3259c69fd5" width="100%" frameborder="0" style="border: none; background: transparent; display: block;" scrolling="no" onload="resizeIframe(this)"></iframe>

<script>
function resizeIframe(iframe) {
  iframe.style.height = '7300px'; // Desktop-specific adjustment (Always adjust desktop first, once you find the correct height adjust for mobile below)
    setTimeout(function() {
    try {
      // Attempt to get dynamic height (may fail due to cross-origin-resource-sharing limitations)
      const height = iframe.contentWindow.document.body.scrollHeight;
      if (height > 100) { 
        iframe.style.height = height + 'px';
      }
    } catch (e) {
    
      console.log('Could not auto-detect height, using fallback');
    }
  }, 500);

  
  if (window.innerWidth <= 768) {
    iframe.style.height = '10300px'; // Mobile-specific adjustment (Usually 33% bigger than Desktop)
  }
}


function handleResize() {
  const iframe = document.getElementById('newsletter-iframe');
  if (iframe) {
    iframe.style.height = '100px';
    resizeIframe(iframe);
  }
}

window.addEventListener('resize', handleResize);
window.addEventListener('orientationchange', handleResize);
</script>]]></content><author><name>Etienne Lefebvre</name></author><category term="Newsletter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">November Monthly Meeting</title><link href="/2025/09/29/November-Meeting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="November Monthly Meeting" /><published>2025-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/09/29/November-Meeting</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/09/29/November-Meeting.html"><![CDATA[<figure class="text-center">
  <img src="/assets/img/november_meeting.png" width="80%" />
</figure>

<p>Our November Monthly Meeting will feature a crash course on the <strong>2026 city of Ottawa draft budget</strong>, what it means for the financial solvency of our city, and how to best get involved with the budget process, with a special highlight on <strong>delegation opportunities</strong> at upcoming city council and standing committee meetings.</p>

<p><strong>Join us for our first monthly meeting, meet new people, learn about our priorities, and consider taking that first small step to get involved. All experience levels are welcome!</strong></p>

<p>🗓️ <strong>Date:</strong> November 6, 2025<br />
🕕 <strong>Time:</strong> 6:15 PM – 7:15 PM<br />
📍 <strong>Location:</strong> St. Peter’s Lutheran Church, 400 Sparks Street</p>

<p>Strong Towns Ottawa Monthly Meetings are open to the public. Anyone can join!</p>

<p>And don’t forget to join our <strong>post-meeting hangout starting at 7:30 PM</strong> at the <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/ffa9aQZ9JHpJUiA28">3 Brasseurs pub</a> on 240 Sparks Street</p>]]></content><author><name>Etienne Lefebvre</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The City Needs to be Bold with Bank</title><link href="/2025/09/25/the-city-needs-to-be-bold-with-bank.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The City Needs to be Bold with Bank" /><published>2025-09-25T21:51:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-25T21:51:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/09/25/the-city-needs-to-be-bold-with-bank</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/09/25/the-city-needs-to-be-bold-with-bank.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/uploads/250528%20Mayfair%20Bus%20Photo%20Smaller.jpg" alt="250528 Mayfair Bus Photo Smaller.jpg" /></p>

<h2 id="last-nights-open-house">Last Night’s Open House</h2>

<p>Last night the City of Ottawa held an open house for the <a href="https://engage.ottawa.ca/bank-street-active-transportation-and-transit-priority-feasibility-study">Bank Street Study</a> that looked at improving transit, active transportation, and accessibility to Bank Street, in the section between Lansdowne and the 417. To anyone who’s familiar with <a href="https://strongtownsottawa.ca/bank/">our work</a> on this, you’ll know we want this area to be made into a wonderful area for shoppers, residents, commuters, and businesses.</p>

<p>The city presented their proposal, which seeks to turn the Northbound peak morning travel lane into a bus only lane, and likewise for the Southbound. It would also turn both outer lanes into bus-only lanes during large events (things like Redblacks games that see ~20,000+ people come to Lansdowne) on weekends, which only occur ~15 times a year according to the city. There were two very tiny sections near Fifth avenue and the bridge to Old Ottawa South that will see full 24/7 bus lanes.</p>

<h3 id="the-citys-current-proposal">The city’s current proposal</h3>

<p><img src="/uploads/OpenHouseBankStreetRedesignVisual.avif" alt="OpenHouseBankStreetRedesignVisual.avif" /></p>

<p>After the city’s presentation, where they discussed the benefits of improving transit in the corridor, about how small of a percentage (7%) of the local parking is on-street along Bank, about how under-utilized that parking is (sits less than 50% used for the majority of the day), and so many more points that would lead you to the conclusion that full dedicated bus lanes were the obvious choice, we were then presented with a watered down version that tried to “compromise”, but instead gave us a half-baked result that seeks to please “everyone” and instead pleases no one.</p>

<h2 id="how-did-people-respond">How did people respond?</h2>

<p>The city opened the floor to allow for questions and comments, and for the next hour we heard from all sorts of citizens. We heard from young students, we heard from retired citizens, we heard from Glebe residents, we heard from parents of children who want safer cycling, we heard from citizens who cycled in, pedestrians, shoppers, workers, transit riders, and more. <strong>Every single person without question (besides the BIA representative) said this project does not go far enough.</strong> Person after person got up and said we need to be bolder. They said we need to have a solution that works for everyone, and this half-measure works for nobody.</p>

<p>They pointed out that this does absolutely nothing for small and medium events like 613Flea, the farmer’s market, the winter market, concerts, smaller sporting events, etc… They pointed out that this does nothing for the students who rely on the 6 and 7 and often bus outside of “peak hours”. They pointed out that this does nothing for weekends where Bank turns into a parking lot as cars try to parallel park and slow down everyone else behind them. They pointed out that this does nothing for the other 16 hours of the day where buses are forced to pull in and out between parked cars, getting bogged down, leading to less reliable service and higher costs to run our transit system. They pointed out that cyclists will still be at risk of getting doored when trying to cycle safely along this vital corridor to visit local shops.</p>

<p>Every single group said unquestionably that they wanted more from the city, and not more parking, but more bus lanes! As someone who attends a LOT of public engagements and open houses (yes — I’m a loser) I have truly and honestly never in my life seen something this overwhelming. In a room full of close to 150 people, all we heard was rounds of applause at every single comment of the over 20+ speakers that said they wanted better bus lanes, that this vision did not represent them, and that it didn’t go far enough.</p>

<p>All that we unfortunately heard back was about finding a “balance”. But who are we balancing with? The fewer than ~140 parking spots along Bank that mostly sit un-used? The misguided opinion that those spots, and not the local residents that visit shops on a regular basis, the cyclists who come multiple times a month, the workers at the stores who rely on our deteriorating transit system, are the ones that actually make those businesses thrive? We certainly didn’t hear from anyone, besides the representative for the local BIA, that the few parking spots on Bank Street were so vital that we should under no circumstances remove any of them to make the rest of the street better and more accessible to people.</p>

<h2 id="how-vital-is-this-on-street-parking">How “vital” is this on-street parking?</h2>

<p>As we can see from the city’s data below, the on-street parking is extremely under-utilized on Bank. Generally best practices for parking usage is that you want it to not be sitting mostly empty, otherwise that space could be much better used for other needs (such as improving transit). Ideally you want your parking to be used with ~70-85% so that on each block you’ll typically have 1 or 2 spaces available for anyone to use that needs it. You also don’t want to have your parking used so much that it is impossible to find a spot, as that incentivizes people to  circle the block over and over to find parking. As you can see, the on-street parking on Bank rarely if ever gets close to that sweet spot, and is very often sitting closer to below 50%, or above 90%, a.k.a. being severely misused.</p>

<h3 id="bank-on-street-parking-north">Bank On-Street Parking North</h3>

<p><img src="/uploads/bankStreetParkingUsageGlebeNorthWithPurple.png" alt="bankStreetParkingUsageGlebeNorthWithPurple.png" /></p>

<h3 id="bank-on-street-parking-south">Bank On-Street Parking South</h3>

<p><img src="/uploads/bankStreetParkingUsageGlebeSouthWithPurple.png" alt="bankStreetParkingUsageGlebeSouthWithPurple.png" /></p>

<p><strong>Legend :</strong></p>

<p>Red : Parking under 50% utilization</p>

<p>Orange : Parking utilization between 50-60%</p>

<p>Yellow : Parking utilization between 60-75%</p>

<p>Green : Parking utilization between 75-85%</p>

<p>Purple : Parking utilization over 85%</p>

<p>A quick note about the above 90%, you’ll find that this almost only ever occurs at times when the parking is free (Sundays, and in the evenings). What this means is that we’re not actually charging appropriately for the parking at those hours, because it is being over-utilized, and someone who might really want that parking cannot get it, because people are leaving their cars in a location where they might not actually need to.</p>

<h2 id="other-parking-options">Other parking options</h2>

<p>One thing to keep in mind is the 2nd Avenue garage. It is a garage that fits as many parking spots as the the whole section of Bank Street from Lansdowne to the 417. Yet according to city data, and our own experience every time we are out there at some of the busiest times, it sits almost completely un-used. If parking was so in demand, surely this parking garage would be much more full than the data tells us it is, right?</p>

<p>Well… the data seems to tell us a different story. As you can see below, using the same colouring scheme as the on-street parking, we can quite shockingly see that there’s a LOT of red here. There is almost literally never a time where the parking is being used over 50% in the 2nd avenue garage, yet it’s less than a 10 minute walk to almost the whole section of Bank Street, almost perfectly situated right in the middle.</p>

<p>Also important to keep in mind is the below is only publicly available parking, but there are also plenty of businesses that have parking of their own. Kettleman’s, Popeye’s, McDonald’s, etc… all have their own parking lots, which means there’s even more available parking on the street that gets missed here.</p>

<p>According to city data of close to 3000 responses the vast majority of people coming to Bank are happy to walk 5-10 minutes to get to the shop they want to go, and the beautiful thing about a bit of walking is they might encounter a new shop along the way that they didn’t know about! This is wonderful for businesses, we know from plenty of data that the more people you have walking near your store the better your business does.</p>

<h3 id="second-avenue-garage-parking-floors-1-and-2-short-term">Second Avenue Garage Parking Floors 1 and 2 (Short term)</h3>

<p><img src="/uploads/bankStreetOffStreetParkingLevels1And2WithPurple.png" alt="bankStreetOffStreetParkingLevels1And2WithPurple.png" /></p>

<h3 id="second-avenue-garage-parking-floors-3-and-4-long-term">Second Avenue Garage Parking Floors 3 and 4 (Long term)</h3>

<p><img src="/uploads/bankStreetOffStreetParkingLevels3and4WithPurple.png" alt="bankStreetOffStreetParkingLevels3and4WithPurple.png" /></p>

<h3 id="574-bank-street-parking-lot-near-highway">574 Bank Street Parking Lot (Near Highway)</h3>

<p><img src="/uploads/bankStreetOffStreetParking574BankWithPurple.png" alt="bankStreetOffStreetParking574BankWithPurple.png" /></p>

<h2 id="so-where-does-this-leave-us">So where does this leave us?</h2>

<p>Currently the project is clearly not ambitious enough. It seeks to find “balance”, but the “balance” is mostly just keeping the status quo. The bus lanes will only be swapping out what were previously regular travel lanes in each direction during peak hours.</p>

<p>The numbers that the city quotes as “improvements” to transit might not jump out at you initially (they quote about 1 minute improvements), but the reason for this is because they only compare the improvements to how the transit currently runs when there are 2 travel lanes in the peak direction. What this completely misses is that much of the delays that the buses see in these areas is not during the times when the lane they are loading and unloading passengers on is a travel lane, but instead during the rest of the time when the outer lanes are parking.</p>

<p>Each time a bus has to pull in and out of a stop is adding significant delays as it tries to merge back into heavy traffic. With a corridor as busy as this, with so many cars, pedestrians, cyclists, etc… that leads to much more stress and confusion for bus operators, who already have a stressful enough job. This also leads to an extremely complicated, delayed, and potentially dangerous, experience for everyone else on the road, including drivers.</p>

<p>What this means is that during the times when we would hope to see the most significant benefit, which is during hours where parking is allowed on the outer lanes, we have done absolutely nothing to improve the situation. Yet these are the times when our transit needs the most help.</p>

<p>Our city should have done studies to see how much transit would have been improved in cases where parking was removed. The answer would have almost surely been substantially. We need to be bolder than this, the busiest bus corridor in our city, with 2 of the busiest buses in our whole network, deserve better than this. If we cannot take even the busiest bus corridor in the city and make improvements to it, what hope does our broader transit network have? Bus lanes are a quick, easy, and proven solution to making transit better.</p>

<p>24/7 bus lanes would make this street more straightforward by reducing signage, it would make it more efficient for drivers and transit users, it would help cyclists have a lane where they don’t have to worry about dooring, it would help transit users get to where they need to go quickly and efficiently, businesses would benefit by being more accessible to people, pedestrians would have better visibility on the street with no parked cars blocking their sight lines, it would cut down on parallel parking causing congestion, and SO MUCH MORE.</p>

<p>The best part of all of this, is it would only require us to move a tiny amount of the overall parking in the area off of the street, and as we’ve already seen, the rest of the parking capacity is easily able to soak all of that up, and more.</p>

<p>We strongly urge the City of Ottawa to take advantage of this opportunity to be <strong>BOLD</strong>. The current proposal is timid and too small to make a meaningful change considering how long it took to get here (the first open house was in June of last year). If we somehow end up being incorrect in our bet, then we fully support the city revisiting the project to make the necessary adjustments. This is the Strong Towns way: taking bets that are easy to implement, provide meaningful incremental change, and build up over time to further improve our beautiful city for everyone; be they a shop owner on Bank Street, a Student heading to class, a distant shopper, or a local resident.</p>]]></content><author><name>Marko Miljusevic</name></author><category term="Transit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Property Tax Revenue Analysis and Dataset</title><link href="/2025/09/04/property-tax-revenue.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Property Tax Revenue Analysis and Dataset" /><published>2025-09-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/09/04/property-tax-revenue</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/09/04/property-tax-revenue.html"><![CDATA[<p>Tax revenue maps typically report the overall tax levy on a property in dollars. This approach favours large format developments but hides how efficiently it’s generating municipal revenues. Efficiency matters!</p>

<p>We know that the cost of most city services scale with distance. The cost of roads, transit, sidewalks, snow clearing, etc… increase the more spread out we are. So shouldn’t the city consider the revenue per hectare of a development instead, to ensure the services it provides to those residents are sustainably funded?</p>

<p>This is what we refer to as “tax revenue density”. You divide the amount of tax a property generates by its area. At scale, this type of metric is useful to show development patterns that are efficient at building wealth for the city, and which are less productive. The same way we can compare fuel efficiency of cars, dividing the tax bill by area permits apples-to-apples comparisons between properties. Large format properties are no longer favoured just because they are big.</p>

<figure class="text-center">
<img src="/assets/img/revenue_efficiency.png" />
</figure>

<p>Efficient land use has been a cornerstone principle of Strong Towns and firms like Urban 3 have been successful in generating stunning city renderings that show where a city is generating wealth efficiently in intuitive ways.</p>

<h2 id="ottawas-revenue-density">Ottawa’s Revenue Density</h2>

<p>The City of Ottawa recently launched an online <a href="https://propertytaxes-taxesfoncieres.ottawa.ca/en" target="_blank">property tax lookup tool</a>. Paired with the list of all city addresses, available through <a href="https://open.ottawa.ca/" target="_blank">Open Ottawa</a>, we were able to put together and visualize most of the 400,000 city addresses and collect tax information for years 2023 and 2024.</p>

<p>The data is surprisingly comprehensive. When all the property taxes are compared to the city’s official <a href="https://open.ottawa.ca/datasets/26c90c66fb8042778cd7e3685365a918_0/explore">Taxes by Ward 2022-2024</a>, the data is 94% accurate. Coverage by <a href="https://ottawa.ca/en/living-ottawa/laws-licences-and-permits/laws/laws-z/zoning-law-no-2008-250/zoning-law-2008-250-consolidation">zoning groups</a> is also very good with over 97% of Part 6 - Residential, and 84% of Part 10 - Mixed-Use / Commercial properties successfully found.</p>

<p>When we look at the city-wide average revenue density by zoning group we see how efficient Mixed-Use Downtown properties are. At the bottom, we find R1, R2, Arterial Mainstreet and oddly Transit Oriented Development (maybe it just needs more time? We’ll look at this in a future post).</p>

<figure class="text-center">
<img src="/assets/img/revenue_zoning_code.png" />
</figure>

<h2 id="comparing-properties">Comparing Properties</h2>

<p>In Ward 9 Knoxdale-Merivale, the property with the highest assessed value is a huge lot with multiple big box stores, a fast-food restaurant, and a gym. This property also pays the highest amount of municipal taxes. However, when you account for how much space it takes up, mostly for parking, it generates slightly over $130,000 per hectare. By comparison, the two most efficient revenue generating properties in the ward generate municipal revenues up to 9 times more efficiently, and people live there!</p>

<figure class="text-center">
<img src="/assets/img/revenue_ward_9.png" />
</figure>

<h2 id="citywide-3d-maps">Citywide 3D maps</h2>

<p>These data can also be rendered in 3D, like Urban 3. Here is the revenue density for all properties within the City of Ottawa’s urban boundary. It’s important to note that the height of these shapes do not represent building heights, but rather revenue density per property (did we really need to label downtown?).</p>

<figure class="text-center">
<img src="/assets/img/revenue_urban_markup.png" />
</figure>

<h2 id="seeing-the-effect-of-development-patterns">Seeing the Effect of Development Patterns</h2>

<p>We can zoom in and start appreciating where value is being generated. For example, the city-leading property generates revenue at a rate of $15,000,000 per hectare. We also see how a sidewalk facing strip mall in Rideau-Vanier and a modest 3-story townhome in Kitchissippi outperform a car dealership by several factors.</p>

<figure class="text-center">
<img src="/assets/img/revenue_downtown.png" />
</figure>

<p>In the suburbs we see the same story. Large  format car-centric businesses like Costco and Landmark Cinema’s are dwarfed in revenue density by townhomes and condos. From the data it seems clear that car-centric development patterns dilute the value of properties and erodes the city of wealth.</p>

<figure class="text-center">
<img src="/assets/img/revenue_kanata.png" />
</figure>

<h2 id="sharing-these-data">Sharing these data</h2>

<p>We hope that these types of analyses can encourage pragmatic discussions between residents, community associations, city councillors and staff. To that end, Strong Towns Ottawa has a number of resources that we encourage you to use including the city wide property tax dataset. <a href="/resources/">See the resources page</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Bickerton</name></author><category term="Finances" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Tax revenue maps typically report the overall tax levy on a property in dollars. This approach favours large format developments but hides how efficiently it’s generating municipal revenues. Efficiency matters!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">September Newsletter</title><link href="/2025/09/02/September-Newsletter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="September Newsletter" /><published>2025-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/09/02/September-Newsletter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/09/02/September-Newsletter.html"><![CDATA[<iframe id="newsletter-iframe" src="https://eocampaign1.com/web-version?p=05807a58-72ca-11f0-97df-237306d6f0b6&amp;pt=campaign&amp;t=1756818061&amp;s=e973e6a463371fb14780ac2d833bbfa401b8e532707ab11cd412a6f5fb626015" width="100%" frameborder="0" style="border: none; background: transparent; display: block;" scrolling="no" onload="resizeIframe(this)"></iframe>

<script>
function resizeIframe(iframe) {
  iframe.style.height = '8200px'; // Desktop-specific adjustment (Always adjust desktop first, once you find the correct height adjust for mobile below)
    setTimeout(function() {
    try {
      // Attempt to get dynamic height (may fail due to cross-origin-resource-sharing limitations)
      const height = iframe.contentWindow.document.body.scrollHeight;
      if (height > 100) { 
        iframe.style.height = height + 'px';
      }
    } catch (e) {
    
      console.log('Could not auto-detect height, using fallback');
    }
  }, 500);

  
  if (window.innerWidth <= 768) {
    iframe.style.height = '13400px'; // Mobile-specific adjustment (Usually 33% bigger than Desktop)
  }
}


function handleResize() {
  const iframe = document.getElementById('newsletter-iframe');
  if (iframe) {
    iframe.style.height = '100px';
    resizeIframe(iframe);
  }
}

window.addEventListener('resize', handleResize);
window.addEventListener('orientationchange', handleResize);
</script>]]></content><author><name>Etienne Lefebvre</name></author><category term="Newsletter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Parking Day 2025</title><link href="/2025/08/31/Parking-Day.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parking Day 2025" /><published>2025-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/08/31/Parking-Day</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/08/31/Parking-Day.html"><![CDATA[<hr />

<h2 id="event-details">Event Details</h2>

<p><strong>📅 Date &amp; Time:</strong> Friday, September 19, 2025, 11:00 AM – 7:00 PM</p>

<p><strong>📍 Location:</strong> East side of Bank Street (between 1st and 5th Ave) in the Glebe</p>

<h2 id="what-is-parking-day">What is PARK(ing) Day?</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.myparkingday.org/">PARK(ing) Day</a> is a global event where community groups temporarily transform on-street parking spaces into vibrant, people-centric public spaces (called “parklets”) for a whole day. It’s an excellent opportunity to reimagine what our streets could look like with more space for people, not just cars. It’s also a great tabling opportunity, allowing you to engage with the public and reach communities you may not have previously connected with.</p>

<h2 id="interested-in-getting-involved">Interested in getting involved?</h2>

<p>If your organization wants to participate please let us know by dropping us an email at <a href="mailto:team@strongtownsottawa.ca">team@strongtownsottawa.ca</a>! We’ll help you plan your parklet. And please add your project to the <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSe-UPTeIgh233ye9S6KQev7dZRYF0zAKC3uiThVRJeVtqP1Kw/viewform?usp=dialog">official PARK(ing) Day Map</a>.</p>

<h2 id="how-it-works-during-parking-day">How it works during Parking Day:</h2>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Claim your spot:</strong> We recommend you arrive at 11am to secure a parking spot. Find an empty parking space and pay for it ($3/hour from 9am-5:30pm). Feel free to take more than one spot if you feel like your parklet installation requires more space.</li>
  <li><strong>Set up your parklet installation:</strong> Get inspired with the <a href="https://www.myparkingday.org/how-to">PARK(ing) Day How-To Manual</a>. It’s always a good idea to use cones, planters, or barricades to define and protect your space.</li>
  <li><strong>Take pictures:</strong> This is a global event, be sure to share your photos on social media using the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#ParkingDay2025</code> tag so that people across the world can see Ottawa’s creative parking day installations!</li>
</ol>

<p><em>Inspiration from other Parking Day events!</em></p>

<div class="row">
    <div class="col-md-6 mb-4"> <!-- Added mb-4 here -->
        <figure>
            <img src="/assets/img/dsafasdfasf.png" alt="Flea market at Landsdowne" class="img-fluid" />
        </figure>
    </div>
    <div class="col-md-6 mb-4"> <!-- Added mb-4 here -->
        <figure>
            <img src="/assets/img/finishedParklet_Seattle.jpg" alt="Flea market at Landsdowne" class="img-fluid" />
        </figure>
    </div>
    <div class="col-md-6 mb-4"> <!-- Added mb-4 here -->
        <figure>
            <img src="/assets/img/Parking-Day-2015_DC.jpg" alt="Farmer's market at Landsdowne" class="img-fluid" />
        </figure>
    </div>
    <div class="col-md-6 mb-4"> <!-- Added mb-4 here -->
        <figure>
            <img src="/assets/img/Parking-Day-Singapore-2018.jpg" alt="Farmer's market at Landsdowne" class="img-fluid" />
        </figure>
    </div>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Event" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our Blueprint for Building Better in Canada</title><link href="/2025/08/28/Build-Canada-Homes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our Blueprint for Building Better in Canada" /><published>2025-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/08/28/Build-Canada-Homes</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/08/28/Build-Canada-Homes.html"><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0;">
  <img src="/assets/img/logo3.png" style="width: 200px; height: auto; object-fit: contain;" />
</div>

<p>The federal <a href="https://housing-infrastructure.canada.ca/bch-mc/market-sounding-guide-sondage-marche-eng.html">Build Canada Homes</a> (BCH) program aims to address Canada’s housing crisis by accelerating the amount of housing that is built. But we must build more than just housing units; we must build communities that are financially resilient and actually pay for themselves.</p>

<p><strong>Below is the official feedback we submitted</strong>, urging the government to abandon the sprawl-based model that has left our cities with massive infrastructure time bombs. We advocate for incremental growth, leveraging existing infrastructure, and abolishing restrictive zoning to allow for more density.</p>

<hr />
<p>To the Build Canada Homes Team,</p>

<p>We appreciate the opportunity of providing input. It is our core belief that Canada’s housing strategy should not only produce units quickly, but also build places that endure financially, socially, and culturally.</p>

<p>Our past offers valuable lessons in the way cities used to be managed. The most successful cities have always grown incrementally, with durability in mind, and in compact neighborhoods that paid for themselves quickly over a reasonable period of time. This type of incremental growth brought wealth and opportunities for all people involved while creating the identity of what we have come to love as Canada.</p>

<p>However, it has been 80 years since we embarked on an experiment, a model of urban development never tried before, and it has proven now to result in the opposite of what cities used to offer. Today, our cities are inflated economic liabilities, unable to adapt to demographic and environmental changes, and over-dependent on a single mode of transportation along with the debt necessary to build and maintain the infrastructure for it.</p>

<p>BCH is a welcome initiative from the Federal Government, and we hope that by following these 6 guidelines it will generate lasting, positive impacts in our built environment:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Use Time-Tested Methods of Urban Growth</strong>: Favour incremental development patterns within existing neighborhoods that do not rely on complex financing, rather than the now common large-scale and single-use subdivisions. These historic patterns have produced the most resilient cities, both financially and socially.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Design Housing That Creates Lasting Value</strong>: Encourage building forms and site layouts that foster street life and can evolve over time to support diverse uses. Prioritize design principles, material selection, and construction methods that ensure durability and long-term livability.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Plan for Financial Productivity and Housing Affordability</strong>: Adopt a value-per-hectare analysis to ensure proposed developments generate sufficient long-term tax revenue to cover future infrastructure maintenance, and use the Federal leverage to build, assist, manage, and fund non-profits in the affordable housing space.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Leverage Existing Infrastructure Before Expanding</strong>: Densify where streets, pipes, and utilities already exist, as it reduces the infrastructure deficit and is a better use of public money.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Enable Gentle Density and Mixed Uses</strong>: Force the abolition of restrictive zoning, change financing models and review building codes, to allow for greater options in housing types (five over ones with commercial podiums, mid-rises with single staircases, family-sized units and so on) that blend into existing neighbourhoods.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Promote Innovation Without Losing Sight of Proven Principles</strong>: Support new techniques for modular and prefabricated construction to accelerate delivery, but combine this with design standards that respect the traditional urban form and land uses that actually improve our communities.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>By combining the willingness of the federal government with new building techniques and time-tested urbanism, Build Canada Homes can deliver not just houses that most can afford, but beautiful and financially resilient communities that will stand the test of time and keep alive the Canadian culture we all cherish.</p>

<p>Sincerely,<br />
<strong>Strong Towns Ottawa</strong><br />
<em>August 28th, 2025</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Letters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">August Newsletter</title><link href="/2025/08/01/August-Newsletter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="August Newsletter" /><published>2025-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/08/01/August-Newsletter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/08/01/August-Newsletter.html"><![CDATA[<iframe id="newsletter-iframe" src="https://eocampaign1.com/web-version?p=28f5b398-6d68-11f0-865d-05ecf714d2a3&amp;pt=campaign&amp;t=1754060700&amp;s=51c4c01aa7980a838f9ff0982dd4fac65a30c810abc44a9df4b367e1a724588a" width="100%" frameborder="0" style="border: none; background: transparent; display: block;" scrolling="no" onload="resizeIframe(this)"></iframe>

<script>
function resizeIframe(iframe) {
  iframe.style.height = '4250px'; // Desktop-specific adjustment (Always adjust desktop first, once you find the correct height adjust for mobile below)
    setTimeout(function() {
    try {
      // Attempt to get dynamic height (may fail due to cross-origin-resource-sharing limitations)
      const height = iframe.contentWindow.document.body.scrollHeight;
      if (height > 100) { 
        iframe.style.height = height + 'px';
      }
    } catch (e) {
    
      console.log('Could not auto-detect height, using fallback');
    }
  }, 500);

  
  if (window.innerWidth <= 768) {
    iframe.style.height = '6250px'; // Mobile-specific adjustment (Usually 300-400px higher than Desktop)
  }
}


function handleResize() {
  const iframe = document.getElementById('newsletter-iframe');
  if (iframe) {
    iframe.style.height = '100px';
    resizeIframe(iframe);
  }
}

window.addEventListener('resize', handleResize);
window.addEventListener('orientationchange', handleResize);
</script>]]></content><author><name>Etienne Lefebvre</name></author><category term="Newsletter" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The High Cost of Sprawl; Ottawa’s Infrastructure Time Bomb</title><link href="/2025/07/07/Infrastructure-Time-Bomb.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The High Cost of Sprawl; Ottawa’s Infrastructure Time Bomb" /><published>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/07/07/Infrastructure-Time-Bomb</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/07/07/Infrastructure-Time-Bomb.html"><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0;">
  <img src="/assets/img/logo3.png" style="width: 200px; height: auto; object-fit: contain;" />
</div>

<p><strong>SUMMARY:</strong> Ottawa faces a growing infrastructure crisis as the cost to maintain and replace its extensive 9,600 km water, wastewater, and stormwater pipe balloons. The current replacement cost of this infrastructure is $51.2 billion and is projected to rise significantly in the coming years. Much of this burden stems from decades of low-density suburban growth, which generates insufficient revenue to cover long-term maintenance. To avoid escalating costs and financial strain, the City must halt new sprawling developments and prioritize infill, intensification, and sustainable funding strategies.</p>

<hr />

<p>On June 11, 2025, the Ottawa City Council received and adopted the funding strategy described  in the Long Range Financial Plan VI – Water, Wastewater and Stormwater (Rate) Supported Programs (LRFP VI), a strategic document that outlines the City’s financial direction and priorities over the next decade. Through careful analysis of this report and the City’s publicly available but technically complex GIS (geographic information system) data is the beginning of a trend, and a revelation, that could have major implications for the City’s future: the cost of maintaining Ottawa’s water infrastructure is about to balloon out of control.</p>

<p>After the Second World War, Ottawa experienced a significant population boom, and the vast majority of its growth was outwards. Spurred by highway construction, and the rise of automobile ownership, new suburban communities began to emerge beyond the traditional urban core. Neighbourhoods like Nepean, Gloucester and Alta Vista, have since evolved into major residential hubs, largely driven by the postwar ideal of homeownership and demand for large, single-family houses. Between 1950 and 2020, Ottawa’s population more than quadrupled, from under 250,000 to over 1 million, with much of that growth taking place in the suburbs.</p>

<p>As Ottawa’s footprint expands, so too does the demand for critical underground infrastructure, systems such as water, wastewater, and stormwater networks that are costly to install, expensive to maintain and even more costly to eventually replace. To support its growing population, Ottawa now oversees an extensive underground infrastructure network totalling more than 9,600 kilometres of water, wastewater, and stormwater pipes, roughly the equivalent of driving from Ottawa to Los Angeles and back.</p>

<p>Unsurprisingly, the city’s oldest pipes are concentrated in the pre-war urban core. Of the approximately 1,000 kilometres of pre-war pipe infrastructure, about 180 kilometres are still in use and range in age from 75 to 150 years old. The first wave of suburban growth in the 1950s and 60s contributed an additional 1,800 kilometres of pipe, while the remaining 7,500 kilometres support areas developed more recently. Because so much of this infrastructure was installed within a relatively short time span, much of it will require renewal or major repairs around the same time — and the cost of doing so will be enormous due to the sheer volume of pipe involved. Ottawa faces an infrastructure time bomb that has already begun ticking.</p>

<figure class="text-center">
<img src="/assets/img/pipes.png" />
</figure>

<p>Every meter of pipe laid to support new developments represents a long-term financial commitment for the City. While development charges may have helped cover the initial capital costs of installing these new pipes in suburban developments, it is water bills collected from residents that fund their ongoing maintenance and eventual replacement. The problem? Low-density suburban neighbourhoods don’t generate enough revenue to pay for the infrastructure they depend on.</p>

<p>In 2017, the City’s Long Range Financial Plan estimated the total replacement value of its water infrastructure—the cost to replace the entire network of pipes, treatment remaining 7,500 kilometres support areas developed more recently. Because so much of this infrastructure was installed within a relatively short time span, much of it will require renewal or major repairs around the same time — and the cost of doing so will be enormous due to the sheer volume of pipe involved. Ottawa faces an infrastructure time bomb that has already begun ticking.</p>

<p>stations, and related assets—at $20.9 billion. Just eight years later, this figure has surged by over $30 billion, reaching $51.2 billion, a staggering increase of 145%. For additional context, the current report proposes investing $4.37 billion over the next 10 years in infrastructure renewal—more than a 30% increase over the inflation-adjusted annual
renewal investment of $3.15 billion allocated in 2017. Given the City’s existing pipe network and the planned expansion for new developments, these renewal costs are expected to continue rising unchecked, highlighting an urgent and growing financial challenge.</p>

<p>The real test for the City will come when the 7,500 kilometres of pipes, all installed within the last 55 years, reach the end of their lifespan and require replacement. While underground infrastructure is a major concern, it represents only part of the broader challenge. Other essential assets, such as roads, bridges, transit systems, and public facilities, also require substantial long-term maintenance and eventual replacement. In total, the cost of this infrastructure far exceeds what low-density development can realistically sustain.</p>

<p>The numbers are clear: replacing the City’s aging pipes will require billions of dollars in future investment. However, the communities that rely on these pipes cannot shoulder the
financial burden on their own. While these realities may be difficult to confront, deferring action will only worsen the problem. The longer the City delays addressing the fiscal and
structural consequences of its growth model, the more severe and costly the eventual interventions will become.</p>

<p>The first and most critical step is to implement a moratorium on approving any new lowdensity developments that would add to the existing infrastructure burden. Without halting new sprawl development, the City risks further compounding its infrastructure liabilities. Strong Towns Ottawa urges the City to begin rejecting low-density housing proposals like
the Tewin development, which would significantly expand Ottawa’s sprawl footprint. To address the City’s growing infrastructure challenges and ensure long-term fiscal sustainability while being cognizant of the housing crisis, Strong Towns Ottawa makes the following recommendations:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Reform Growth:</strong> Align new developmental approvals with fiscal sustainability benchmarks. Prioritize infill and intensification in areas with existing infrastructure capacity.</li>
  <li><strong>Revenue Alignment:</strong> Explore area-specific infrastructure levies or long-term asset renewal funds tied to suburban communities.</li>
  <li><strong>Plan Ahead:</strong> Instead of waiting for a wave of infrastructure renewals to overwhelm the City or delaying until critical systems begin to fail, we should take a proactive approach. Replacing aging pipes in a timely manner not only mitigates risk but also creates opportunities to modernize the above ground infrastructure.</li>
</ul>

<p>The strain on the City’s infrastructure isn’t simply due to aging assets, but stems from a dated approach to urban development that failed to account for its long-term financial consequences. This model, driven by unsustainable growth and mounting debt, has created significant costs that future generations will be forced to bear. Unless corrected, the City will face rising costs that outpace its ability to pay, resulting in service degradation, infrastructure failure, and higher taxes. To ensure its long-term viability, it is essential that the City align its lands-use and infrastructure strategies with financial realities. The City’s financial stability depends on whether it is willing to confront the cost of its past choices and build smarter from here forward.</p>

<p><em>Strong Towns Ottawa</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Letters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>